

Aerial-Robotics Controls Researcher

Autonomous Systems Lab, ETH Zürich, LEE J 314, Leonhardstrasse 21, 8092 Zürich, Switzerland

■ tstastny@ethz.ch | □ (+41) 79 883 7765 | ● US Citizen | ★ tstastny.qithub.io

Summary.

Aerial-robotics controls researcher with 8+ years experience in aerodynamic modeling, simulation, system identification, state estimation, control, planning, and flight-testing of fixed-wing, multi-copter, and hybrid vertical take-off and landing (VTOL) unmanned aerial vehicles (UAVs).

Grants: Authorship of **successful** research proposals with funding totaling >**1.7M USD**.

Publications: As of November 18, 2020, peer-reviewed publication count: 31, h-index: 11, citation count: 492 (source: Scholar).

Mentorship: Supervision of 2 Ph.D. students and 50+ M.Sc. and B.Sc. theses. Lecturer for 2 M.Sc. courses. TA for 2 B.Sc. courses.

Field experience: Organization/contributions of/to aerial-robotic field-campaigns in the Arctic, Antarctic, Brazilian Amazon, and Swiss/Italian Alps.

Education_

2014 - 2020 **ETH Zürich**, Zürich, Switzerland

Ph.D. in Robotics, supervised by Prof. Roland Siegwart in the *Autonomous Systems Lab*Dissertation: *Low-Altitude Control and Local Re-Planning Strategies for Small Fixed-wing UAVs*

2012 - 2014 University of Kansas, Lawrence, KS, USA

M.Sc. in Aerospace Engineering (with Honors), GPA: 4.0/4.0

2012 **TU Delft**, Delft, Netherlands

Coursework in Systems & Control and Aerospace Engr. M.Sc. Programs

2008 - 2012 **University of Kansas**, Lawrence, KS, USA

B.Sc. in Aerospace Engineering, GPA: 3.7/4.0

Research Experience_

Since 6/2020

Autonomous Systems Lab (ASL), ETH Zürich – Post-Doctoral Researcher

- Supervise and coordinate PhD and Masters student research activities related to measurement, aerodynamic modeling, system
 identification, and control of fixed-wing and hybrid, tilt-wing, VTOL UAVs, results including:
 - automatic tilt-wing control video:

 https://youtu.be/pSXEnHUY2_4
 - stabilized deep stalled flight video: 🗷 https://drive.google.com/file/d/1JpexWpThE5TOrnXN1Og9uz9aQ5ysgh-m/view?usp=sharing
- Lead a team of PhD and Masters students on an (ongoing) project for autonomous, high-speed, aerial, vision-based payload recovery.

2014 - 2020

Autonomous Systems Lab (ASL), ETH Zürich – PhD Research Assistant

- Core researcher on EU search-and-rescue robotics projects SHERPA and ICARUS, organizing multiple university and industry partners in collaborative robotic field demonstrations.
- Interfaced with customers and industry partners within the ESA precision-farming project *SOLAR3* to deliver a reliable automatic, multi-hour endurance, surveying drone solution to non-expert end-users.
- Developed and deployed efficient wind-aware guidance and control algorithms for fixed-wing, multi-copter, and VTOL tailsitter UAVs in extreme weather conditions safely stabilizing and preventing run-away of the aircraft. (see Publications)
- Developed and deployed Nonlinear Model Predictive Control (NMPC) algorithms for/on fixed-wing UAVs which mitigate actuator faults, prevent stall, exploit wind, and utilize vision-based terrain measurements for obstacle avoidance.
- Conducted performance optimization and developed automatic take-off, landing, and cruise control design for the *AtlantikSolar UAV*, resulting in an **81.5 hour endurance world record** solar-powered flight for aircraft <50kg (2015)

 http://www.atlantiksolar.ethz.ch/index.html%3Fp=670.html and 26 hour, fully autonomous, search-and-rescue payload equipped flight (2016)

 http://www.atlantiksolar.ethz.ch/index.html%3Fp=931.html

2012 - 2014

Center for Remote Sensing of Ice Sheets (CReSIS), University of Kansas – Masters Research Assistant

- · Conducted research on control and planning for fixed-wing UAVs including multi-agent avoidance and formation strategies.
- Contributed to the design, integration, and Antarctic deployment of a polar-conditioned fixed-wing UAV with integrated dual-frequency ground-penetrating radar.

Skills_

Programming C++, Python, Matlab/Simulink

Software GNU Linux, Robotic Operating System (ROS), Git, Jenkins CI, Unigraphics NX (CAD)

Hardware 3D Prototyping, Radio controlled (RC) piloting of small fixed-wing aircraft and multi-copters

Field Projects

- Supervised/Managed student/engineering work on platform and payload development towards autonomous, beyond visual line-of-sight (BVLOS), drone-based deployment of GNSS monitoring stations on the Gorner Glacier, Switzerland. (2019) video: Thttps://youtu.be/1tvYj1aGEUc
- Contributed regulatory documentation and flight-stack verification for the first networked (via industry partners Swisscom, INVOLI, and v2sky),
 BVLOS flight in Switzerland over Lake Neuchâtel. (2019) video: Thttps://youtu.be/ks-TiJP3dxs
- Organized/Lead UAV operations in Northwest Greenland for a glacier monitoring field campaign, resulting in *first-ever* autonomous, BVLOS, solar-powered flights of a UAV in a polar region. (2017) website: C* https://sun2ice.ethz.ch, video: C* https://youtu.be/wyS6W1t_ryQ
- Organized/Lead field operations together with Swissnex Brazil and Brazilian Civil Aviation Authorities resulting in *first-ever* solar-powered flights of a UAV over the **Amazon rainforest** and the aerial monitoring/mapping of an oil spill on the Rio Pará.
- 8-week deployment as mission planner and ground station operator for autonomous, BVLOS flights of a radar-integrated UAV in Antarctica, resulting in first-ever glacial bed-rock sounding via a UAV. (2014) https://cresis.ku.edu/content/research/field-programs/antarctica#2013

(Selected) Publications

A full list of publications may be found 🎓 https://scholar.google.ch/citations?user=R5Fs1A4AAAAJ&hl=en, or is available upon request.

Optimization-Based Control:

- T. Stastny and R. Siegwart. "Nonlinear Model Predictive Guidance for Fixed-wing UAVs Using Identified Control Augmented Dynamics". In: International Conference on Unmanned Aircraft Systems (ICUAS). (2018).
- S. Verling, **T. Stastny**, G. Bättig, K. Alexis, and R. Siegwart. "Model-based Transition Optimization for a VTOL Tailsitter". *In: IEEE International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA*). (2017).

VTOL, Hybrid Platform Identification and Control:

- D. Rohr, **T. Stastny**, S. Verling, and R. Siegwart. "Attitude and Cruise Control of a VTOL Tiltwing UAV". *In: IEEE Robotics and Automation Letters*. (2019). **C* https://youtu.be/pSXEnHUY2_4**
- C. Olsson, S. Verling, **T. Stastny**, and R. Siegwart. "Full Envelope System Identification of a VTOL Tailsitter UAV". *In: AIAA Guidance, Navigation, and Control (GNC) Conference*. (2021).
- S. Fuhrer, S. Verling, **T. Stastny**, and R. Siegwart. "Fault-tolerant Flight Control of a VTOL Tailsitter UAV". *In: IEEE International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA)*. (2019).

Disturbance Modeling and Rejection:

- T. Stastny and R. Siegwart. "On Flying Backwards: Preventing Run-away of Small, Low-speed, Fixed-wing UAVs in Strong Winds". In: IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems (IROS). (2019). This https://youtu.be/oM690L029kM
- D. Hentzen, **T. Stastny**, R. Siegwart, and R. Brockers. "Disturbance Estimation and Rejection for High-Precision Multirotor Position Control". *In: IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems (IROS)*. (2019).
- Y. Demitri, S. Verling, **T. Stastny**, A. Melzer, and R. Siegwart. "Model-based Wind Estimation for a Hovering VTOL Tailsitter UAV". In: IEEE International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA). (2017).

Long-term Flight Autonomy:

• P. Oettershagen, **T. Stastny**, T. Hinzmann, K. Rudin, T. Mantel, A. Melzer, B. Wawrzacz, G. Hitz, and R. Siegwart. "Robotic Technologies for Solar-powered UAVs: Fully Autonomous Updraft-aware Aerial Sensing for Multiday Search-and-rescue Missions". *In: Journal of Field Robotics* (JFR). (2018). C https://youtu.be/8m76Mx9m2nM

Mentorship & Teaching.

- Supervised 2 PhD Students (ongoing), 24 Masters Theses, 18 Masters Semester Theses, and 14 Bachelor Theses at ETH Zürich. (2014 Present)
- Coached 3 ETH Zürich Focus Projects teams of 8-12 B.Sc. students who develop a robotic product from A to Z:
 - Dipper a flying, diving, swimming, and re-emerging, swept-wing UAV. video: ♂ https://youtu.be/q_9tSHTW1xE
 - ftero a VTOL UAV for airborne wind energy (year 1 and 2)
 - VertiGo a wall-riding robot. Resulted in a patent. video: ☑ https://youtu.be/KRYT2kYbgo4
- Co-Lecturer for ETH Zürich M.Sc. course "Robot Dynamics" (2015-Present).
- Guest Lecturer for University of Kansas Aerospace M.Sc. course "Optimal Control" (2013).
- Teaching assistant for University of Kansas B.Sc. courses "Introductory Topics in Mathematics" and "Elementary Statistics". (2010 2012)

Awards.

- O. Hugo Schuck Best Paper Award (2018) for American Control Conference (ACC) paper: "Gone with the wind: Nonlinear Guidance for Small Fixed-wing Aircraft in Arbitrarily Strong Windfields".

 This://a2c2.org/awards/o-hugo-schuck-best-paper-award
- United States Department of Defense Antarctica Service Medal (2014)
- University of Kansas Aerospace Undergraduate Researcher Award (2012)